Vítor Nascimento Lourenço

✓ vitornaslourenco@gmail.com

 $\square +55 \ 21 \ 99817 \ 2109$

vlourenco.com.br
lattes.cnpq.br/7172413417236996
in linkedin.com/in/lourencovitor
github.com/vitornl

In a Nutshell

I am currently a master candidate in Computing, with an emphasis on Artificial Intelligence, at the Computing Institute of Federal Fluminense University (IC/UFF). I hold a Bachelor's degree in Computer Science from the IC/UFF, and I hold an Informatics Technical Diploma from the Federal Center for Technological Education Celso Suckow da Fonseca (CEFET/RJ). My work is within the area of Computer Science, with an emphasis on Artificial Intelligence. My research interests rely on the following themes: machine learning over relational data, neural-symbolic integration, and knowledge representation.

EDUCATION

Master in Computing

Niterói, Brazil

Federal Fluminense University, Institute of Computing

2019 - Present

- o 2019-Present: National Council for Scientific and Technological Development Fellow
- o 2019-Present: Student member of Database Research Group from the Systems and Information

Bachelor in Computer Science

Niterói, Brazil 2014 - 2018

- Federal Fluminense University, Institute of Computing
 - o 2014-2018: Student member of Database Research Group from the Systems and Information Engineering Lab
 - 2014-2016: Founder and leader of Data Science Club UFF

Informatics Technician

Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Federal Center for Technological Education of Rio de Janeiro, School of Informatics and Computing

2011-2014

o 2012-2014: Student member of Applied Computing Research Group

EXPERIENCE

IBM Research Research Intern Rio de Janeiro, Brazil August 2018 - Present

o In the first year of internship at IBM Research, I support the development of learning-based solutions on knowledge engineering for natural resource challenges. Meanwhile, I develop the Python framework, called HKpy, for IBM Hyperlinked Knowledge Graph technologies. HKpy was the first asset in the research group to be published and maintained open-source (https://github.com/ibm-hyperknowledge/hkpy). During the second year of internship, I worked in a client's project, where I research and developed a system for managing cyclic machine learning workflows.

LDSOFT

Niterói, Brazil

Research Intern

July 2017 - July 2018

 During my internship, I was mainly responsible for coordinating a project to develop a trademark image retrieval system using computer vision and pattern recognition techniques. Further, I was a member of the development team of a natural language processing system for trademark name matching.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

• Languages

- Portuguese (Fluent Native).
- English (Advanced Understanding, reading, writing, and speaking).
- o German (Basic Understanding, reading, and writing).

• Programming Languages

- Advanced knowledge in C, Python, and TeX.
- Basic knowledge in R, and Java.

• Data Science and Machine Learning Tools

- o Advanced knowledge in NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, and Scikit-Learn.
- o Basic knowledge in Pandas, PyTorch, Tensorflow, OpenCV, and Airflow.

• DevOps Tools

o Basic knowledge in Travis, Docker, and Kubernetes.

- Best Computer Vision/Image Processing/Pattern Recognition Main Track Paper Award Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (SIBGRAPI), 2019.
- Best Work Award in the Workshop of Undergraduate Works Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (SIBGRAPI), 2019.
- Master Fellowship
 National Council for Scientific and Technological Development Fellowship, 2018.

PUBLICATIONS

- Moreno, M.; Lourenço, V.; Sandro S. R.; Costa, P., Brandão, R.; Civitarese, D.; Cerqueira, R.. Managing Machine Learning Workflow Components. International Journal of Semantic Computing, 2020 (to appear).
- Azevedo, L.; Souza, R.; Brandão, R.; **Lourenço, V.**; Costalonga, M.; Machado, M. O. C.; Moreno, M.; Cerqueira, R.. Adding Hyperknowledge-enabled data lineage to a machine learning workflow management system for oil and gas. First Break, v. 38, p. 91-95, 2020.
- Moreno, M.; Lourenço, V.; Sandro S. R.; Costa, P., Brandão, R.; Civitarese, D.; Cerqueira, R.. Managing Machine Learning Workflow Components, In 2020 14th IEEE International Conference on Semantic Computing (ICSC).
- Lourenço, V. N.; Silva, G. G.; Fernandes, L. A. F. . *Hierarchy-of-Visual-Words: a Learning-based Approach for Trademark Image Retrieval*. In 2019 32nd Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (SIBGRAPI), 218-225.
- Souza, R.; Azevedo, L.; Lourenço, V.; Soares, E.; Thiago, R.; Brandão, R.; Civitarese, D.; Brazil, E. V.; Moreno, M.; Valduriez, P.; Mattoso, M.; Cerqueira, R.; Netto, M. A. S.. Provenance Data in the Machine Learning Lifecycle in Computational Science and Engineering. In: 2019 IEEE/ACM Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS), 2019, Denver. 2019 IEEE/ACM Workflows in Support of Large-Scale Science (WORKS), 2019. p. 1.
- Fiorini, S. R.; Lourenço, V. N.; Santos, R. C. M.; Costa, P. B.; Moreno, M. . Towards Leveraging the Music Industry with Hyperknowledge. In: 2019 International Conference on Artificial Intelligence for Industries, AI4I, 2019, Laguna Hills. Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence for Industries (AI4I), 2019.
- Lourenço, V.; Mann, P.; Guimarães, A.; Paes, A.; Oliveira, D.. Towards Safer (Smart) Cities: Discovering Urban Crime Patterns Using Logic-based Relational Machine Learning. In 2018 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), 1-8.
- Nery, M.; Santos, R.; Santos, W.; Lourenço, V.; Moreno, M.. Facing Digital Agriculture Challenges with Knowledge Engineering. In: 2018 First International Conference on Artificial Intelligence for Industries (AI4I), 2018, Laguna Hills. 2018 First International Conference on Artificial Intelligence for Industries (AI4I), 2018. p. 118.
- Lourenço, V.; Mann, P.; Paes, A.; Oliveira, D. . SiAPP: Um Sistema para Análise de Ocorrências de Crimes Baseado em Aprendizado Lógico-Relacional. In 2016 XII Brazilian Symposium on Information Systems (SBSI), 168-175.
- Lourenço, V. N.; Souza, U.; Ogasawara, E. S. . *Utilização de Algoritmos Genéticos para a Elaboração do Quadro de Horários do Ensino Médio-Técnico Integrado do CEFET/RJ*. In ENCompIF CSBC, 2014, Brasília. ENCompIF II Encontro Nacional de Computação dos Institutos Federais, 2014. p. 1-4.